hey it's professor Dave, let's talk about
carbon
you may have heard that carbon is the
element of life, but what does that
mean? what determines whether an atom is
of carbon in the first place?
an atom consists of positively charged protons
neutrons which have no charge, and
negatively charged electrons
an element is defined by the number of
protons in the nucleus
one proton is hydrogen, two is helium
3 lithium, 4  beryllium, 5
boron and six is carbon. the number of
neutrons and electrons can change but
by definition any atom with six protons
is a carbon atom
how do they form? hydrogen the simplest and
most abundant of all
elements accumulates into clumps due to
gravity which become stars
the tremendous inward pressure triggers
nuclear fusion which is when protons and
neutrons smash together and fuse
many elements including carbon and
larger ones like iron
are made in stars. much larger ones need
the immense energy a supernova
explosion
or particle accelerators here on earth.
so what's so special about carbon?
let's look at the electrons. carbon atoms
have six. the first two are in the inner
shell
and the other four are the so-called
valence electrons in the outer shell
these are the ones available for bonding
with other atoms which happens when two
atoms share two electrons
because elements in this part of the
periodic table want to have eight
electrons in the outermost shell
carbon has a tendency to make four bonds.
these can be single
double or triple bonds and with many
different elements. in addition while
an atom that's bound to two or three other
atoms will adopt a linear or flat shape
a carbon atom that's bound to four other
atoms will take on a three-dimensional
shape
because that's how the electron clouds
on the four atoms can be as far away
from each other as possible
so it's the ability of carbon to bond in
a wide variety of shapes with so many
elements
including itself that makes it so
special. also
carbon-carbon bonds are strong enough to
be stable but not so strong that they
can't break and rearrange
which makes them excellent building
blocks. when by itself
carbon has many allotropes, or ways an
element can be arranged
there's the graphite in your pencil
which consists of slippery sheets of
carbon that rub off easily
there's diamond, the hardest substance known
and we can even make interesting
structures like nanotubes and fullerenes
that's just carbon by itself. when
combined with hydrogen
oxygen, and nitrogen and a few other
elements it makes all the diverse
structures in your body
including carbohydrates, proteins, and DNA.
we can take nature a step further and
synthesize novel materials with an array
of purposes
putting carbons in the empty spots in an iron
lattice makes it stronger
we call this steel which is used in most
large structures we know today
teflon, a carbon-fluorine polymer is a
non-stick substance that is highly
resistant to chemical degradation
and carbon based synthetic drugs like
inhibitors that can silence a faulty
enzyme
hold the prospect of curing so many
diseases. that's a lotta reasons to love
carbon
it really is the element of life. see you
next time